Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
本系列基于并受 锡吕·玛塔吉·涅玛拉·德维的教导所启发，
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
旨在探索两个相互关联的领域之间 的演化关系，
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
这两个领域在粗糙与精微的层面上 表达了人类的知觉。
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
它致力于阐明当前科学 对人类神经解剖学的理解， 特别是对自主神经系统的理解，
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
与传统瑜伽文献中描述的
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
所谓“精微系统”之间的 这种复杂的相互作用。
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最终，本系列试图带领观众 踏上这段探索之旅，
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
透过锡吕·玛塔吉·涅玛拉·德维所教的冥想法， 来体验这些关系。
Hello and welcome to yet another milestone
欢迎大家来到我们学习旅程中的 另一个里程碑，
in our learning journey with our guest, Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
我们的嘉宾是阿希什·普拉丹医生。
We have had some very interesting conversations thus far
到目前为止，我们进行了非常有趣的对话，
and I am really looking forward to another intriguing discussion today with him.
我非常期待今天与他进行 另一场引人入胜的讨论
Welcome, Dr. Ashish.
欢迎，阿希什医生。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Thanks for having me back, Monikaji.
谢谢你再次邀请我，莫妮卡。
We'll start with the question,
我们将从这个问题开始：
which is the relationship between the autonomic nervous system
自主神经系统 与我们今天讨论的
and the energy center that we are discussing today,
能量中心，第四个能量中心
which is the fourth one
之间的关系。
and which organs does this energy center relate to?
这个能量中心与哪些器官有关？
So as we have said in the previous episodes,
正如我们在前几集所说，
as we look at the Sahaj principles
探讨霎哈嘉的原则
and the relationship between energy centers and the organs that it controls,
以及能量中心与其所控制的 器官之间的关系时，
the fourth energy center, also called the Anahata chakra,
被称为心轮（Anahata chakra） 的第四个能量中心
controls multiple absolutely vital organs.
其实控制着多个 绝对至关重要的器官。
The first one of course is the heart.
第一个当然是心脏。
The second one is the entire respiratory system, which is the tracheobronchial tree,
第二个是整个呼吸系统， 也就是气管支气管树， (tracheobronchial tree)
which is the trachea, the bronchi, and the lungs, both of them.
其包括了气管、支气管 和我们的双肺。
And another gland, which is called a thymus gland,
还有另一个腺体叫做胸腺 （thymus)，
which sits here in front of the sternum
它位于胸骨的前方，
and it is related to our immunology and we'll come to that later.
它与我们的免疫学有关， 我们稍后会谈到这一点。
That is what this energy center controls.
这些就是此能量中心所控制的。
To get into a little more detail, this energy center controls the heart
再细说一点， 这个能量中心可能是透过心脏神经丛，
probably through the cardiac plexus.
控制着心脏。
The cardiac plexus is a group of nerves
心脏神经丛是一组神经，
that have both parasympathetic and sympathetic components
它们同时具有自主神经系统 的副交感神经和交感神经
of the autonomic nervous system.
组成部分。
We have said the autonomic nervous system has two components,
我们说过自主神经系统 有两个组成部分：
parasympathetic, which is rest and digest,
副交感神经—— 它负责休息和消化，
sympathetic that is more related to flight and fight.
及交感神经—— 则更多与战斗或逃跑反应有关。
And today we are going to discuss this extremely critical component
今天我们将讨论这个 极其关键的组成部分
or this critical aspect of human physiology.
或者说人类生理学中 这个关键的方面。
So the cardiac plexus controls the heart rate,
所以心脏神经丛控制着心率
as well as the force of contraction of the heart.
以及心脏的收缩力。
And both those things are very important.
这两者都非常重要。
With that, it also helps to regulate our blood pressure.
与此同时，它也帮助 调节我们的血压。
So that's as far as the heart is concerned,
关于心脏而言，就是这样。
and we'll come to that a little later in today's session.
我们稍后会在今天的节目中 谈到这一点。
The other component in how this chakra controls
这个能量中心也控制着 另一个组成部分，
the other most important organs within this anatomical space
即这个解剖空间内 最重要的器官——
are of course our lungs and the tracheobronchial tree.
肺和气管支气管树。
And that is controlled through the vagus nerve,
这是通过迷走神经 (vagus nerve) 控制的，
not the cardiac plexus.
而不是心脏神经丛。
The vagus nerve we have discussed previously
我们之前讨论的迷走神经，
is a nerve that originates in the brain, in the midbrain.
是一条起源于中脑的神经，
And it is a predominant aspect
它是副交感神经系统中
of the parasympathetic nervous system.
重要的一面。
So it is through the vagus nerve that both the lungs,
所以透过迷走神经，
as well as the trachea and the bronchi,
双肺、气管和支气管得以被控制，
which is like a tree that allows the air to come in,
后两者就像一棵树，让空气进入它，
oxygen to be exchanged, so on and so forth.
进行氧气交换等等。
So that is the importance of this energy center.
所以这就是此能量中心的重要性。
Once again to paraphrase,
再总结一下，
through the cardiac plexus, this energy center controls the heart,
透过心脏神经丛， 这个能量中心控制着心脏、
its heart rate, and its contractility.
它的心率和收缩能力，
And then through the vagus nerve,
然后透过迷走神经
controls the function of the lungs
控制着肺部
and the entire respiratory system.
和整个呼吸系统的功能。
It also controls the functioning of the thymus gland,
它也控制胸腺的功能，
which is an endocrine gland,
这是一个内分泌腺体，
which is an immunologically very important gland, but we'll come to that a little later.
在免疫学上是非常重要的腺体， 我们稍后会再谈到它。
So when we talk about this energy center, is there a relationship between this energy center
所以当我们谈论这个能量中心时， 它与神经系统之间
and the nervous system at a human evolutionary level
在人类演化层面上
or maybe at the embryological level?
或者在胚胎学层面上 有什么关系吗？
Absolutely, this energy center is tremendously fascinating. At an embryological level,
绝对有，这个能量中心很有趣。 在胚胎学层面上，
what happens is when the embryo is formed,
当胚胎形成时，
it is just a group of cells
它只是一群细胞，
and then, as everybody knows,
然后，大家都知道
it starts off at the zygote and then it starts dividing.
它从受精卵开始， 然后就开始分裂。
And what is formed initially is a single line of cells
最初形成的是 一条单行的细胞，
and within that single sort of line,
在那条单行排列中，
it's like a column of cells, it has a cephalic end, which you might say like a head end
它像一个细胞柱，有头端， 你可以说像头部的一端
and a caudal end, which is the back end.
和一个尾端，也就是后端。
And there are cells that are formed at the level of the cephalic end,
在头端形成的细胞，
which means at the head end of this little column of cells,
也就是在这个小细胞柱的头端，
which are later on differentiated into what are called cardiogenic cells.
它之后会分化成所谓的心肌细胞 (cardiogenic cells)。
Cardiogenesis means the genesis of the buds of the heart.
Cardiogenesis（心脏发育） 是指心脏芽的发育。
And these cells are formed
这些细胞形成于
at the head end of this little group of cells in a column,
这个小细胞柱的头端，
and then they migrate downwards
然后它们向下迁移，
as the embryo starts differentiating into multiple organs.
随着胚胎开始分化成多个器官。
And that is how the heart is formed
心脏就是这样形成的，
and thereafter the blood vessels, so on and so forth.
然后便是血管等等。
It is very interesting to know that the origin of the heart as an organ
很有趣的是， 心脏作为一个器官的起源，
actually begins at the apex of the human organism, even as it is being formed.
实际上始于人类有机体的顶点， 即便它还在形成中。
And this has very, very profound implications by way of inference of human spirituality.
这在人类灵性的推论上 有着极为深远的意涵，
And we'll talk more about this also in this episode,
在本集节目中， 我们将进一步讨论这个问题，
but also when we talk about it in the last episode,
但也会在最后一集讨论
when we talk about the seventh energy center.
当我们讨论 第七个能量中心时。
So the origin of the heart literally begins at the crown -
所以心脏的起源字面上始于头顶
or what is the crown end of this little organism.
或者说这个小有机体的顶点。
And by day 21, the heart is already pumping blood
到了第21周时， 心脏已经在输送血液，
to allow for the oxygenation and the health of this organism.
为这个有机体的氧合作用 和健康提供支持。
So from an evolutionary point of view,
所以从演化的角度而言，
this energy center literally controls the existence of the organism,
这个能量中心实际上 控制着这个有机体的存在，
because without that, there would be no organism, the viability of this organism,
因为没有它（能量中心）， 就不会有这个有机体，
that is us, each and every one of us
这个生物——也就是我们， 我们每一个人在
when we were conceived in our mother's womb would not be possible.
母亲子宫中受孕时—— 就不可能有生命力。
So that is at the embryological level.
这是在胚胎学层面上的。
At an evolutionary level, it is obvious,
在演化层面上， 从单细胞细菌中
as we have seen from unicellular bacteria,
很明显可看到，
that when life began in the very first episode, when we talked about the first energy center,
当生命开始时， （我们在第一集谈到 第一个能量中心）
its differentiation, its gradual evolution into multicellular organisms,
它的分化、它逐渐演化成 多细胞生物等，
it is entirely possible that it is due to this energy center,
完全有可能是因为 这个能量中心，
that the better differentiation started happening.
才开始发生更好的分化。
So if you look at these small organisms, let's say fish,
所以如果你看这些 水生生命形式
in the aquatic life forms,
的小生物，例如鱼，
and we look at the circulatory system, it goes on evolving from a single chambered organ,
看看它们的循环系统， 其从一个单腔室器官，即所谓的心脏
so called the heart,
不断演化
from a single chambered organ, it goes to a two chambered organ,
变成两腔室器官，
it then becomes a three chambered organ in birds, for example,
然后变成三腔室器官， 例如在鸟类中，
and then in mammals, such as us, it becomes a fully four chambered heart.
最后在哺乳动物中，比如我们， 变成了一个完整的四腔室心脏。
So this energy center plays that critical role,
所以这个能量中心 从鱼类演化的过程中、
or that has probably played this role in the evolution from fish,
从那些生物、 从两栖动物到陆生动物
and from those kinds of organisms from amphibians to terrestrials,
到鸟类再到脊椎动物， 包括我们人类，
to birds to vertebrates, including us as human beings.
扮演着或可能扮演了 这个关键的角色。
And this has been important because
这之所以重要是因为
as the human body became more and more complex,
随着人体变得越来越复杂，
as vertebrates and mammals became more and more complex,
随着脊椎动物和哺乳动物 变得越来越复杂
the metabolic demand for oxygenated blood was more required.
对含氧血液的代谢需求 越来越大。
That is why the differentiation of the heart
这就是为什么出现了心脏的分化——
between a single chambered right up to a four chambered heart
从单腔室一直到四腔室心脏 以及
with complete partition between the atria, which is on top,
在心房（上部）（atria）和 心室（下部）（ventricle)
and the ventricles, which are below.
之间有完全的隔间。
The left side of the heart deals with oxygenated blood;
心脏的左侧处理含氧血液；
the right side pumps out deoxygenated blood into the lungs.
右侧则将缺氧血液泵入肺部。
All of that organization, if you will,
所有这些组织 或者说整个演化过程
or the entire evolutionary process was governed probably by this fourth energy center.
很可能是由第四个能量中心 所主导的。
Again, to paraphrase, our very existence
再总结下，我们的存在本身
and our continued existence depends on this energy center
以及我们持续的存在 都依赖于这个能量中心，
because it controls the heart and the lungs.
因为它控制着心脏和肺部。
Very nicely explained.
解释得真好。
I think this is really, really very helpful information.
我认为这些信息真的非常有帮助，
So this brings me to just another question
所以这让我想到另一个问题：
that there is this expression that the heart is the spark of life.
有一种说法是 “心脏是生命的火花”，
Now, is there any truth or a spiritual correlation here?
这里面有任何事实 或灵性上的关联吗？
Absolutely. So it is kind of metaphorical,
绝对有。这有点像是比喻，
but if we examine how does the heart function?
但如果我们探讨心脏 是如何运作的，
Within the upper right chamber of the heart, the right atrium,
我们会发现在心脏的右上腔室， 也就是右心房内，
there is a small group of cells.
有一小群细胞。
It is called the sinoatrial node.
它被称为窦房结（sinoatrial node）。
And this is a highly specialized group of cells.
这是一群高度特化的细胞，
We discussed in the very first episode, I believe,
我们在第一集就讨论过，
What causes the generation of an electrical impulse
在任何细胞系统内，
within any cellular system?
是什么原因导致电脉冲的产生？
It is the inflow and outflow of potassium and sodium ions.
是钾离子和钠离子的 流入和流出。
They pass through what are called as ion channels,
它们穿过所谓的离子通道，
and they create a difference in the polarity of the cell membrane.
并在细胞膜的极性上 产生了差异。
And that causes a change in the polarity that creates an electrical current.
这导致极性的改变， 从而产生电流。
In this sinoatrial node, for reasons that we have still not been able to fully fathom,
在这个窦房结中，由于某些 我们仍未完全理解的原因，
the movement of these sodium and potassium ions happens very, very fast.
这些钠离子和钾离子的移动 发生得非常快，
And it happens in a way that literally creates the spark of life,
它的发生方式简直就是 创造了生命的火花，
because it is from here that the impulse is generated
因为脉冲就是从这里产生的，
in the upper right hand side of the heart.
在心脏的右上方，
And from there, it is transmitted downwards from the atria to the ventricles.
然后从心房那里向下传导 到心室。
And when that impulse is transmitted, it causes the heart to contract.
当这个脉冲传导时， 它会导致心脏收缩。
And then it contracts and then it relaxes. It contracts and it relaxes.
然后它就收缩，再放松。 它收缩，然后放松。
And it does that 72 times on an average per minute,
它平均每分钟做72次，
that is literally thousands of times per day,
也就是每天数千次，
and in a lifetime of an average individual,
在一个普通人的一生中
a couple of billion times.
大约是数十亿次。
So this energy, literally this energy is the spark of life.
所以这个能量确实 就是生命的火花。
The spark of life is literally generated within the heart.
生命的火花确确实实地 在心脏内产生。
And this spark, if it goes out of sync,
而这个火花如果脱节
or if it stops, then life is in many ways extinguished.
或者停止了，那么 生命在很多方面就熄灭了。
So there is a lot of physiological truth to the fact
因此，生命的火花 存在于心脏之中，
that within the heart is the spark of life.
这个说法有很大的 生理学根据。
From the spiritual point of view, we say that it is the place
从灵性的角度来看，我们说那是
where the Soul or the Atma resides.
灵魂或阿特曼（Atma）居住的地方。
So there is an absolute synchrony or congruence
阿特曼或灵魂或灵体（spirit） 是真正的生命火花
to the notion that the Atma or the Soul or the Spirit
的灵性观点，
is the true spark of life from a spiritual point of view.
有着绝对的同步性或一致。
And that is what Sahaj is really about, realizing our true selves, self-realization.
这就是霎哈嘉的真正意义—— 实现我们的真我，即自觉。
But from a physiological point of view, there is 100% correlation that the spark of life
但从生理学的角度来看， 生命的火花与心脏
literally resides within the heart.
有百分之百的关联， 它确实存在于心脏之中。
So, Dr. Ashish, when we talk about heart, even as a layman, or whether it's in medicine,
那么阿希什医生，当我们谈到心脏时， 即使是外行人，或是在医学上，
we know of it as a single organ, right?
我们都知道它是一个单一的器官， 对吗？
But I understand that within Sahaj principles, there is something called the center heart
但我知道在霎哈嘉的原则中， 有一个叫做“心轮中部”的东西，
that relates to the sense of protection and security.
它与保护和安全感有关。
So is there any support for this principle at the level of human physiology?
那么在人类生理学层面上， 是否有任何支持这一原则的证据？
Yes, there is.
是的，有的。
So what happens is, from a Sahaj point of view, we have not one but three hearts,
从霎哈嘉的角度来看， 我们不只有一个，而是有三个心轮；
we have one on the left side, one in the center,
我们左边有一个， 中间有一个，
one also on the right side of the human subtle system.
右侧也有一个， 在人类精微系统中。
But essentially, it is
但基本上，它是
the fourth energy center, which we can say has three aspects to it.
第四个能量中心，我们可以说 它有三个面向。
So the center heart is related to
所以心轮中部与胸腺 的功能有关，
or probably governs the function of the thymus gland.
或者说它可能主宰着胸腺的功能。
The thymus gland is a very important immunologic organ,
胸腺（thymus gland)是非常重要的 免疫器官，
because what it does is it produces the white blood cells
因为它的作用是产生 属于T细胞种类的白血球，
of the T variety, which are called thymus derived cells.
又被称为胸腺衍生细胞 (thymus derived cells)。
And these cells play an absolutely critical role in protecting the body from infections.
这些细胞在保护身体免受感染方面 扮演着绝对关键的角色。
Whenever there is an infection -
每当有感染时——
viral, bacterial or parasitic -
病毒、细菌或寄生虫感染——
these are the cells that literally are the soldiers of the body
这些细胞简直就是身体的士兵，
that go out and they attack these foreign organisms, these invaders,
它们会出去攻击这些外来生物， 这些入侵者，
and they destroy them, they help to destroy them.
它们摧毁它们，帮助摧毁它们。
There are also other kinds of white blood cells called B cells. But these - the T cells -
还有其他种类的白血球 称为 B 细胞。但这些——T 细胞——
are lymphocytes, the fighter cells
是淋巴细胞，是帮助保护这个有机体
that help protect the organism.
的战斗细胞。
So the notion of protection comes from that point of view as well.
所以保护的概念也来自那个观点，
It's of interest to know that people who feel insecure or are depressed
值得注意的是， 感到不安全或沮丧的人
tend to have a greater proportion of susceptibility to infections,
往往更容易受到感染
to autoimmune disorders,
或患上自体免疫疾病。
there is a lot of literature around it that people who tend to be depressed,
有很多文献都提到过 容易沮丧的人，
what we call in Sahaja left-sided,
我们在霎哈嘉瑜伽中 称之为偏向左脉的人，
they tend to have a lot of susceptibility to infections
他们往往更容易受到感染，
and sometimes even certain malignancies.
有时甚至会患上某些恶性肿瘤。
So, such a correlation is possible.
所以这样的关联是可能的。
But is there a one-to-one correspondence
但是否存在一对一的
between cause and effect?
因与果对应关系？
The cause and effect relationship over a period of time will become clearer,
随着时间的推移，因果关系 会变得更加清晰，
but it is absolutely clear that at a physical level,
但绝对清楚的是， 在物理层面上，
from an immunologic point of view,
从免疫学的角度而言，
the 4th energy center plays a very critical role in the immune homeostasis
第四个能量中心在免疫平衡方面 扮演着非常关键的角色，
or maintaining the immune profile or immune competence of the organism
或者说维持有机体的 免疫状况或免疫能力，
and allows for our survival.
并使我们得以生存。
And at the same time, from an emotional point of view,
同时，从情感的角度而言，
it tends to give that sense of protection
它往往给予那种保护感，
that allows us to overcome any kind of adversity.
让我们能够克服任何形式的逆境。
Adversity is a fact of life, not every day is all roses.
逆境是生活中的事实， 不是每天都是一帆风顺。
There are difficulties that everybody has to face in their life.
每个人在生活中都必须 面对困难。
It is the way in which you face them.
重要的是你面对它们的方式。
And it is this energy center that provides that support
正是这个能量中心 提供了那种支持，
to individuals to overcome that.
帮助个人克服困难。
Yes, there is very much a sense of providing security
是的，透过这个能量中心的功能，
through the function of this energy center.
确实能提供一种安全感。
So this is really very interesting.
这真的非常有趣。
When we talk about the heart as an organ,
当我们谈论心脏 作为一个器官时，
is there something about the heart which directly relates
心脏是否有什么特质 直接关联到
to the concept of collectivity in any way?
任何形式的集体性概念？
Yes, it's a question I was really looking forward to,
是的，这是我非常期待
to explain.
回答的问题。
So the heart represents a very interesting physiologic paradigm.
心脏代表着一个非常 有趣的生理学范式。
And the paradigm is this, that just a few moments ago,
这个范式是这样的， 就在几分钟前
we described how the electrical impulse that is generated
我们描述了所产生的电脉冲
in the upper right part of the heart travels across the entire musculature.
如何从心脏的右上方 传遍整个肌肉组织。
Now, the heart is a muscular organ,
心脏是一个肌肉器官，
it has no bones in it, it's just a mass of muscle.
它里面没有骨头， 只是一团肌肉。
And when the impulse is conducted, the entire thing happens in less than a second.
当脉冲传导时， 整个过程在不到一秒的时间内发生。
If you're beating 72 times per minute,
如果你的心每分钟跳72次，
obviously one cardiac cycle from contraction to relaxation
显然一个心动周期 从收缩到放松
has to happen in less than one second.
必须在不到一秒的时间内完成。
So it is extremely fast, it's extremely efficient.
所以它非常快，非常有效率。
But the beauty of this is that when the impulse passes
构成心脏的有数百万个细胞，
the entire mass of cells,
当脉冲通过整个细胞群时，
there are millions and millions of cells that constitute the heart.
由这些细胞组成的神经纤维，
The nerve fibers that are made up of these cells,
它们全都一致地收缩，
they all contract in unison.
这是其中美妙之处。
It all happens at once; it's not like one muscle cell says,
这一切同时发生；并不是 像某个肌肉细胞说：
"I will think about it later. Okay. You know..."
“我待会再考虑。 好吧。你知道的…”
It doesn't function that way.
它不是那样运作的，
If it functions that way, that is when we get arrhythmias.
如果它那样运作，我们 就会得到心律不整 (arrhythmias)。
Arrhythmias are a break in the rhythm of the heart.
心律不整是心脏节律的中断。
So when the heart beats, it beats in this very beautiful cyclical rhythm.
所以当心脏跳动时，它以 这种非常优美的周期性节律跳动。
And that is literally what keeps us alive.
这就是维持我们生命的根本。
The moment the heart starts going out of rhythm, that's when we start getting into trouble.
一旦心脏开始失去节律， 我们就会开始遇到麻烦。
Heart attacks can cause arrhythmias
心脏病发作会导致心律不整，
or other things can cause arrhythmias.
或其他事情也会导致心律不整。
So the concept of collectivity as the heart represents is this,
所以心脏所代表的 集体性概念是这样的：
that when there is an impulse, all the cells of the heart,
每当有脉冲时，心脏的所有细胞、
the musculature of the heart, the entire tissue,
心脏的肌肉组织、整个组织、
every cell, every fiber in the heart comes together and contracts together.
心脏中每一个细胞、每一条纤维 都会聚集在一起，共同收缩。
And that is how they work together.
这就是它们共同工作的方式。
There is no notion of a democracy there,
那里没有民主的概念，
where a group of cells says, "No, no, no,
如一群细胞不会说，“不，不，不，
we are not interested in contracting.
我们对收缩不感兴趣。
We'll think about this later. Or we are dissenting."
我们稍后再考虑这个问题。 或者我们持反对意见。”
No, the heart doesn't function that way.
不，心脏不是那样运作的。
It's not a political system. It's not a democratic system.
它不是一个政治系统。 它不是一个民主系统。
It's a system where everything works together.
它是一个所有部分 协同工作的系统，
And it works beautifully harmoniously.
而且它运作得非常优美和谐，
And that is the Sahaj concept of collectivity.
这就是霎哈嘉瑜伽 关于集体性的概念。
We will examine that more when we talk about the fifth energy center.
当我们谈论第五个能量中心时， 我们会进一步研究这一点。
But even at the level of the heart, this is where
但即使在心脏的层面上，
at least for somebody like myself who has a medical background,
对于像我这样有医学背景
and is a Sahaj practitioner, I find that absolutely fascinating
同时也是练习霎哈嘉瑜伽的人， 我觉得这绝对令人着迷，
that when we say we are all part of the heart of a divine power,
当我们说我们都是 神圣力量之心的一部分时，
we are all part of this one existence, we are all cells of a larger being.
我们都是这个同一存在的一部分， 我们都是一个更大存有的细胞。
What does that mean? It actually means even at a physiological level,
这是什么意思？ 它实际上意味着， 即使在生理层面上
it is represented within us that all the cells of our heart,
它也在我们体内得到了体现， 我们心脏的所有细胞、
all the tissues, all the muscle fibers,
所有的组织、 所有的肌纤维、
work together for our benefit for the benevolence of this organism.
为了我们的利益，为了这个 有机体的福祉而共同工作。
And that's how the heart to me at least represents an organ
所以对我来说，至少心脏 所代表的器官
that symbolizes at a physiological, at an anatomical level,
在生理上、解剖学层面上象征着
the spiritual concept of collectivity.
集体性的灵性概念。
It is so fascinating to learn more and more about
能从您这里学到越来越多 关于这样的知识，
all of this from you.
真是太有趣了。
It tells us how nature has created
它告诉我们
such complex mechanisms within everything that exists as life on this planet.
大自然是如何在这个星球的一切， 创造出如此复杂的机制。
This was really very helpful.
这真的非常有用。
And I would like to thank you, Dr. Ashish, for your time today.
我要感谢您阿希什医生， 今天拨冗出席，
And we look forward to meeting you soon
我们期待很快能再见到您。
with our next discussion topic, which will be the fifth energy center.
我们下一个讨论主题 将是第五个能量中心。
Thanks once again.
再次感谢您。
Thank you, Monikaji. It was a real pleasure.
谢谢您，莫妮卡。 我非常荣幸。
See you soon.
再见。
We would like to invite and recommend our audiences
我们想邀请并推荐观众们
to follow the video by the founder, Shri Mataji
观看创始人锡吕·玛塔吉的影片，
and get an experience of this meditation.
并体验这种静坐。
We will talk to you soon in our next episode.
我们下一集再会。
Shri Mataji: The center one I have told you is the heart plexus,
锡吕·玛塔吉：中间的那个我已经 告诉过你们，是心脏神经丛，
which we call as cardiac plexus, and it has got ten sub-plexuses.
我们称之为 cardiac plexus （心脏神经丛），它有十个 副神经丛 （sub-plexuses）——
And the English names for that I will, again, I am going to give you the complete list.
这些英文名称，我会给你们 完整的列表，
I don't know when we'll have time to go to the medical journal,
我不知我们何时有时间去 参考医学期刊，
but I'll find out all of them and I'm going to tell you
但我会把它们全部找出来 然后告诉你们
what they call it in medical terminology.
它们在医学术语的名称。
But they know that there are ten sub-plexuses
但他们知道有十个副神经丛
which are supplying to the muscles of the heart, to the lungs
向心脏的肌肉、向肺部、
and to the right side lungs, and that's how they divide it.
和肺部右侧（他们是这样划分的） 供应能量。
Keep your eyes closed.
请闭上眼睛
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
首先，请把你的右手 放在你的心脏上。
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
左手一直朝向我。
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
现在，在这里，你必须在你的心中， 带着全然的真诚说： 母亲，我就是那個灵（真我 spirit）吗？
Ask the question three times in your heart.
在你的心中问这个问题三次。
This is a very fundamental question.
这是一个非常根本的问题。
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
现在把右手 移到你胃部的左侧，
in the upper part.
在上方的位置。
Here press it.
在这里按压它，
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
现在，这是你的导师中心， 你的指引，你的古鲁 Tattva（导师原则）， 如人们所说。
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
所以问一个问题： 母亲，我是自己的导师吗？
This is the question to be asked three times.
这个问题要问三次。
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
现在把你的右手向下移到 腹部的下半部。
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
这是完成所有神圣工作 的中心，
all the pure work is done.
所有纯粹的工作都从这里完成。
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
所以要问六次， 因为这个中心有六个花瓣：
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
母亲，请赐予我纯粹的知识。
Six times you just ask.
就这样问六次。
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
作为这个请求的结果， 昆达里尼（Kundalini）开始被唤醒。
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
现在为了帮助昆达里尼上升， 你必须与她合作。
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
所以请把你的右手 放在左侧，
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
在你腹部的上部， 然后按在胃上。
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
现在，在这里， 为了帮助昆达里尼上升，
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
你必须充满信心地说： 母亲，我是自己的导师。
This you have to say ten times.
这句话你要说十次。
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
这是十条诫律， 你必须说：
that Mother, I am my own master.
母亲，我是自己的导师。
Now, ten times with full confidence.
现在，充满信心地说十次。
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
现在请把你的右手举到 你的心脏。
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
现在，在这里你必须说， 再次充满信心地说，
Mother, I am the Spirit.
母亲，我就是那个灵（真我）。
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
这是真理，你就是真我。
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
但你必须充满信心地说， 母亲，我就是那个灵。
This you have to say twelve times.
这句你要说十二次。
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
现在，人必须知道 全能的上帝是爱的海洋。
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
但最重要的是，祂是宽恕的海洋。
So He forgives.
所以祂会原谅。
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
无论你做错什么，祂都会宽恕。
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
所以不要感到罪疚， 把你的右手
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
放在左侧，在你脖子和肩膀 形成的角落里。
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
现在在这里，你必须说， 再次充满信心地说十六次：
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
母亲，我没有罪疚感。
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
请说出来：母亲，我没有罪疚感。
Sixteen times.
十六次。
I am not guilty at all.
我完全没有罪疚感。
Please say it.
请说这句话。
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
现在将你的手放在你的前额上， 这是一个非常重要的中心。
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
在这里，你必须发自内心地说： 母亲，我宽恕每一个人。
Please say it from your heart.
请发自内心地说。
How many times is not the point.
说多少次不是重点。
Mother, I forgive everyone.
母亲，我宽恕每一个人。
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
现在，有些人可能会说 宽恕很困难。
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
但这是一种幻象， 以为我们不宽恕或我们宽恕，
We do not do anything in both the cases.
在这两种情况下， 其实我们什么也没做。
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
但如果我们不宽恕， 我们就落入了坏人的圈套。
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
所以请诚心地说： 母亲，我宽恕每一个人。
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
现在请把你的手放在后脑勺， 也是同一个能量中心，在后脑部位，
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
让你的头靠在手上， 然后稍微向后推。
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
现在，在这里，你必须说， 为了让你自己安心……
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
因为你总是感到罪疚， 说：“哦，神圣的力量，如果我做错了任何事，
please forgive me.
请宽恕我。”
Please forgive me, from your heart.
请宽恕我。发自你的内心去说。
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
现在请将你的手完全伸直， 把你的手掌中心，
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
放在囟门骨区的顶端， 那是你童年时非常柔软的那块骨头。
Press it hard.
请用力按压它。
Press hard your scalp.
用力按压你的头皮。
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
现在你要转动你的手七次， 一边说这句话——这是你必须请求的：
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
母亲，请赐予我自觉， 因为我不能强迫你。
So you have to ask for it.
所以你必须诚心请求它。
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
转动七次，用力按压， 并非常用力地转动七次。
Slowly saying that.
慢慢地，一边说着这句话。